Guide to the Robert F. Durden Reference Collection, circa 1965-2001
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Robert F. Durden Reference collection circa 1965-2001
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. University Archives
0.5 Linear Feet about 21 Items
Robert F. Durden is a professor emeritus of history at Duke University. He has written numerous articles and several books about the history of Duke University, the Duke Family and The Duke Endowment.
The collection includes reprints of articles and a speech written by Durden about Duke University, the Duke Family, and The Duke Endowment as well as a bibliography of selected works by Durden and clippings. The material ranges in date from circa 1965-2001.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Robert F. Durden Reference Collection was compiled from various sources by University Archives staff for reference and research.
Biographical Note
Robert Franklin Durden was born in Graymont, Georgia in 1925. He earned an A.B. (1947) and M.A. (1948) from Emory University, and a Ph.D. from Princeton University (1952). He served in the U.S. Navy from 1943 to 1946. He was an instructor and fellow at Princeton from 1950 to 1952. He joined the faculty of the History Department at Duke University in 1952, and served as chair of the Department from 1974 to 1980. He has been a Fulbright Professor at Johns Hopkins University and Monash University (Melbourne, Australia), and a visiting professor at several schools. He is now (2005) Professor emeritus. His field is 19th century U.S. history, Civil War and Southern history. He is also interested in the history of the Duke Family, Duke University, the Duke Endowment, and Duke Power Company.
Collection Overview
This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research. It includes reprints of articles and a speech written by Durden about Duke University, the Duke Family, and The Duke Endowment as well as a bibliography of selected works by Durden and clippings. The material ranges in date from circa 1965-2001.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Durden, Robert Franklin
Duke Family
The Duke Endowment
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Related Material
Robert F. Durden Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Speech, Trinity's Past and Duke's Future, Alumni Day, 1965 Apr. 10 (Box 1)
  - Article, A Troublesome Legacy: James B. Duke's Bequests to his Cousins, North Carolina Historical Review, 1973 Autumn
  - Article, The Coming of the Endowment, Duke Alumni Register, 1974 Dec.
  - Article, Origins of The Duke Endowment and the Launching of Duke University, North Carolina Historical Review, 1975 Spring
  - Article, Ignoring Regional Students Detrimental, Short-Sighted, 1985
  - Article, Crises in University Governance: The Launching of Duke University, 1925-1935, Part I: 1925-1930, North Carolina Historical Review, 1987 July
  - Article, Crises in University Governance: The Launching of Duke University, 1925-1935, Part II: 1930-1935, North Carolina Historical Review, 1987 Oct.
  - Article, One Recumbent Too Many - Duke University and the Ackland Art Museum, North Carolina Historical Review, 1988 Oct.
  - Article, The Rebuilding of Duke University's School of Law, 1925-1947, North Carolina Historical Review, 1989 July
  - Article, James B. Duke Wins and Loses: The Partial Collapse of his Grand Design for Perpetual Philanthropy in the Carolinas, North Carolina Historical Review, 1997 Jan.
  - Duke Gardens through the Years, 1997
  - Article, Electrifying the Piedmont Carolinas: The Beginning of the Duke Power Company, 1904-1925, Part I, North Carolina Historical Review, 1999 Oct.
  - Article, Electrifying the Piedmont Carolinas: The Beginning of the Duke Power Company, 1904-1925, Part II, North Carolina Historical Review, 2000 Jan.
  - A bibliography of selected works by Robert F. Durden pertinent to Duke University and the Duke Family, 2001
  - Clippings - desegregation and race relations given by Durden (A74-112)